well what if we grounded in in a
community community like ours
you know where this is a new community
where we we've just formed in really the
last two months we're
almost at our two-month anniversary uh
you know
how would how would you recommend for
example we
what what should we be thinking of in in
setting up
you know our network we're in the middle
you know of crafting roles and
responsibilities and
you know different roles that people are
are taking within the community
or some some will be organizing events
other people will be
you know you know maybe leading
meditations or or other type of sessions
uh
uh others will be working on structure
you know what what what can we take from
your work to help direct us
okay so there's actually a whole lot of
stuff um
let's begin with i'm going to put it in
form of recommendations as opposed to in
the form of
options because the option space is
quite large in terms of recommendations
some things that i would point out
are a network design
one of the variables you can look at is
the degree to which a particular node
and domain which is to say a cluster of
nodes is
specialized or generalized and so
if for example in the military you tend
to have
high levels of specialization in
in for example decision making and so
the the
major function in army has a very
specific domain of in scope of decision
making
and it's very very important that that
particular node know when a decision
is is in its scope if it's too big it
has to go up if it's too little has to
go down like that kind of
structure and notice what happens there
is that once you've made a couple of
commitments
to how you're designing your network a
bunch of other stuff comes with it right
so if you design
a network that is of the sort of a
post-world war ii military
then if you wanted to be effective at
all a lot of
energy a lot of attention a lot of the
capacity given individuals actually has
to be focused on questions like
is this particular area of inquiry
something that
is right for my level of authority or
should i push it down or should i send
it up
um so you may or may not have been
planning on that as being part of what
the time
you're spending people's time on but
ultimately it's part of the
you have to and so it gets smuggled in
and that's a i think a thing that people
miss a lot is that the there's actually
some
natural network design clusters that
once you've made a few choices
a lot of other things follow now in the
context of what you guys are doing what
my sense is there's kind of
or three things that are happening
simultaneously that may be a little bit
of tension that may be a healthy tension
so on the one hand i've mentioned i've
heard you mention the word
community and it feels to me like in the
tone of your voice when you say it
that you actually mean that in the sense
of communitas like a
a group of people who
sense of togetherness or wholeness in
being together
yes um maybe in the monastic sense more
than in the uh
village sense but you know
all in in direction in that way
equally there seems to be a sense of a
horizontal
some sort of mission or objective or
purpose more than just shared values
but interestingly that's oriented
towards something which is
uh how would i say this singular in the
in the domain of purpose which is to say
that
the religion that's not a religion for
example in that document
it feels like that may be a particular
area of interest and as you said
the meaning crisis right there is a not
just a calling
that there's a gap people are gathered
into this community as a as a
consequence of the
the bell that john is wrong but also
there seems to be an
awareness or intent to
focus in the direction of that calling
so it's not like hey we all gathered for
the meeting crisis but now that it's
just kind of become
a barbecue um but actually a sense that
there's something about this column that
has meaningfulness to it no pun intended
and therefore should have a sensitivity
or uh
so again that kind of that pulls more in
the direction of a monastic community
and less in the direction of a uh
sort of general purpose where people
live um
if you know if you look at the topology
of monastic communities
it's actually interesting because there
is there's a real distinction you know
villages have a different
natural topology and by necessity than
monastic communities the monastic
community has to have more formal
structure it actually has to have
certain levels of certain roles that
people play
and a lot of rituals that keep
uh disciplined attention while still
maintaining the real integrity of
community like the
many monks who i know feel like the
level of
live human relationship and community
and monasteries is much stronger than
any other place they've ever been
but this would imply uh
orienting towards um
like ritual being thoughtful about
having certain kinds of ritual practices
that
create a an easy and ease
to the discipline is necessary to
maintain
integrity in relationship to the purpose
while
well and holding like making relatively
ease full
the the that level of rigor
so that it can then also happen in the
context of community
um you would also want to
because you're doing something in the
domain of community that is
virtual we don't really know it's not
easy human beings naturally do communal
stuff in physical space particularly
around things like food and
kind of viviality uh it's harder to do
that in a virtual space because you
don't have the right
context and signals so i would recommend
playfully and experimentally but
nonetheless
thoughtfully making that an object of
intent
so wonder what kinds of things might
we do to support a deeper felt sense of
humanness like
and do we want to have um if you play
dungeons and dragons or a roleplaying
game
like have our identities have our
identities have a certain level of
richness and playfulness to them so that
when people encounter each other
they're already drawn into something
like how do you render the
texture and feel uh of relationality
that's necessary for community
in a virtual environment in certain you
know aesthetics
is one possible way and playfulness is
another possible way
so that's another chunk so i'm kind of
putting in there the toolkit includes
things like
ritual and intentionally thinking about
creating rituals
largely to increase rigor while also
increasing easefulness
the second one would be to be
intentional
around things like playfulness and the
felt sense
of expression of self into a shared
space
a third and this is now again i'm now
starting to get a little bit more
fluid is um how would i say this there's
a there's a distinction what i would say
is between
uh two kinds of design there's a uh what
i might call
after my forest landry an omniscient
design or a uh
propositional design a blueprint kind um
and a transcendent design or a um
sense oriented design has more of a
feeling of intuitive or
felt sense actually it's not really
intuitive mentions felt sense
and so i might recommend
practices that orient groups of people
who build their capacity in
gathering a shared felt sense
in themselves enhancing their own
capacity of their own felt sense and
then using
the individual and collective capacity
to discern
rightness through felt sense as a
primary mode of collective design and
decision making
in how the the environment progresses
um and and and evolves
that's more oh keep on keep on going
no no i do not want you to stop keep on
going
um so so the two more that come up i'm
actually seeing john in my mind's eye
now and hearing his voice which
uh i can't remember her name she's an
influence of both johns and of dave
snowden's and one of the sort of primary
thinkers
in uh
[Music]
like how complex systems actually emerge
or how you can design for emergence
has to do with sort of enabling
constraints and disabling constraints
and so
thinking in that way and sort of
thinking about this as having a certain
necessary autopoaces to it
is to think about how do you actually
identify what are the appropriate
enabling constraints and disabling
constraints to give
structure while simultaneously
engendering the uh
the surprise the insight and creativity
that actually makes it be a felt organic
space